<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-06-15T03:31:06+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">An Encounter with Causal Inference</title><link href="/blog/2021/An-Encounter-with-Causal-Inference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Encounter with Causal Inference" /><published>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2021/An-Encounter-with-Causal-Inference</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2021/An-Encounter-with-Causal-Inference/">&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Story Begins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ordinary day in March, I was in my instructor’s office chatting with him about life when a book on his shelf caught my eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it all started with The Book of Why (TBW) and a genuine curiosity of how the world works. The read was a disappointment. The book does not examine the questions whose answers I set out looking for (Does there exist true causal relationships, or are they mere illusions? How to define causal relationships? …) Yet the delight was bigger – it introduced me to Pearl’s school of causal inference, its main intuitions, its core concepts (do-calculus, causal diagrams (DAG), Bayesian networks and belief propagation, deconfounding…), and its divergence from traditional econometrics. It fired back at me many new questions that were more manageable and no less intriguing, e.g., how to teach an AI to understand causal relationships (which concerns the dissection of causal phenomena and how they are processed in the human brain)? What are the limitations of representing causal relationships with DAGs? Why isn’t Pearl’s school mainstream?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With wild enthusiasm, I finished the book, deconstructed it, and reconstructed it for presentation purposes in three days. I finally felt like I was no longer trapped in the clouds of endogenous idle thoughts and was placing a foot on the land of normal science. Pearl’s argument was so powerful that I’ve been wearing his lens ever since – I found potential applications of DAG in the context of Rousseau’s social contract, I imagined the possibility of accurately predicting the future given a decent causal network, and millions of questions kept me awake late into the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to know everything about Pearl’s school. My next prey was Causality: Models, Reasoning and Inference. I was lucky to have a wise instructor who pulled me back in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meeting the “enemy”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, I still hadn’t seen the other side of the coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the freshman year summer, I read Introduction to Econometrics (Stock &amp;amp; Watson) and Mostly Harmless Econometrics (Angrist &amp;amp; Pischke). At first I was highly contentious and suspicious of the validity of the traditional econometrician’s way of approaching causal questions. I took a lot of side-notes to argue for why the econometrician’s wrong or at least not fully correct, siding with Pearl, both because I was sincerely in doubt and because I started to prepare for my URA project, “When Pearl Meets Rubin.” But my assertiveness and arrogance subsided as I advanced, and my critical thinking later proved more than beneficial for my understanding of the content – I felt like engaging in a lively conversation with the authors. My question regarding one paragraph is addressed in the next. And this unprecedented feeling of interaction deeply touched and inspired me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to appreciate how the econometric approach to causality is self-contained, statistically rigorous, intuitive, highly applicable and beautifully delicate as in how it reduces unimaginable complexities to means and regressions. However, my previous exposure to Pearl impeded me from being fully convinced by, e.g., Rubin’s causal model and its variations (IV, DID, RDD). They are convenient, but in a sense they still do not touch the core or the exact mechanisms of causality. Causality for econometrics seems to still be a black box whose input and output are extensively studied but whose inner workings are undiscussed. Another analogy would be, the secret of causality lies in a trench, but econometrics builds only extravagant cruises and is only concerned with the surface of the sea. Econometrics may argue that since most people never leave the “surface”, and since causal impacts are impactful only when it is conducted to the “surface”, there is no need to study what’s beneath the surface or in this case, what “causality” itself really is. In my opinion, econometrics is a study about rather than of causality. Even though this would usually suffice, the “indirectness” of econometrics is both the source of its power and its fatal flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This observation is verified by one of my current courses, Quantitative Methods for Policy Evaluation (ECO3211). We read classic papers that estimate the causal impact of income shocks on Tanzanian witch murder with rainfall as IV, or the causal impact of air pollution on obesity with thermal inversion as IV, or the causal impact of cable TV on Indian female status using DID. I have to admit that sometimes the design of the quasi-experiments are ingenious, but I must also insist that it is not enough. No matter how many tests are passed, the result is just not convincing. Each identification strategy has some assumptions that are almost impossible to be rigorously proven (exclusive restriction for IV, parallel-trend assumption for DID, etc.). Econometrics is constantly compromising, but these compromises may not be as necessary as it preaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only referential value remains, not direct value, can’t directly apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another flaw of Rubin’s school is its inflexibility to changes, i.e., the lack of generalizability/external validity. Every paper has a different specified equation. Any major changes in context or setting requires remodeling and new yet highly homogeneous calculations. Pearl’s causal inference engine has much higher adaptability, because it is pre-established by human brain, not dependent on data, and can be partially adjusted without having to remodel from scratch. One crowning achievement of the “Causal Revolution” is being able to predict the effects of an intervention without actually enacting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a sense, Pearl’s school is structural while econometrics is relatively reduced-form. It remains in question whether this reduction can be justified. However, it also remains in question whether Pearl’s school can ever be attained or put into use. In fact Pearl’s school is far from perfect, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rivalry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One major concern I have for Pearl is that his approach is much closer to the philosophical aspects of causality, thus he inevitably has to deal with disentangling his science from philosophy where nothing is absolutely certain. He implies in TBW that his focus does no go beyond the day-to-day causality experienced by the human brain, which he takes as given and uses as a benchmark for the cultivation of strong AI. But this causality is not well-defined. What does an arrow in a DAG really mean? Can I draw an arrow between smoking and lung cancer? Or should I draw arrows between smoking, particles that go into the lung, body chemicals in the lung, blood circulation, cancer cells, and then lung cancer? The looseness of scale makes DAG less rigorous. However, putting restrictions on scale would require discussion that enters the realm of philosophy, which would further complicate the issue at stake. So in some sense, although DAG is rather structural compared to Rubin’s causal model, it is still reduced-form compared to real causality. Returning to the sea analogy, Pearl tries to build submarines, which is an improvement from the cruises of econometrics in the aspect of depth, but it is still not enough. However, I do hope he addresses this problem more in Causality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicality is another concern regarding Pearl. To what extent is DAG applicable? It is relatively ideal only if it can be effectively applied. When Prof. Ye Luo visited our school I asked for his opinion on Pearl, and he replied that DAG is already widely used in natural sciences such as biochemistry (causes and effects are obvious), but he doubted if it will ever become mainstream in social sciences where causality is too complicated. I agree with him. According to what little knowledge of DAG I have acquired through TBW, it is far from equipped if it is to deal with actual social phenomena where hundreds and thousands of factors at simultaneously at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various other concerns, but I retain them now as my meager knowledge of Pearl’s school does not allow me to pose serious objections to it. I do hope to read Causality as soon as I’m freed from this semester’s coursework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although due to heavy coursework I haven’t had much time to read CI-related materials this semester, I can’t wait to further my investigation into my project, “When Pearl Meets Rubin,” by learning more about both schools. I’m in the process of reading Imbens’ 2020 paper Potential Outcome and Directed Acyclic Graph Approaches to Causality: Relevance for Empirical Practice in Economics and can only exclaim that it is a gorgeous piece of work! But reading it is also a bit discouraging since he almost covers all my ideas and thoughts with depth and breadth I can hardly hope for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of curiosity I did attend a weekly seminar organized by Bochum University (“Why Do People Believe Weird Things? Bayesian Brains, Conspiracy Theories, and Intellectual Vices”) and read through Notes on Bayesian Confirmation by Michael Strevens. They helped me learn more about how Bayesian update works, why it works, etc. Bayesian networks is central to Pearl’s CI framework, and I wanted to get familiarized with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when I’m not doing much reading, my mind is constantly contemplating on my project, drawing inspiration from seemingly irrelevant observations and courses. For example, when Prof. Song introduced Nash Bargaining as an alternative for the kind of bargaining we normally learn in game theory classes, I realized it bore a significant similarity to the relationship between PO and DAG, with the former being nonchalant to what exactly happens inside the black box and the latter especially drawn to it. The interesting thing is, the latter is mainstream in game theory whereas the former is mainstream in CI. It may be because game theory is primarily concerned with mechanisms and these mechanisms are manageable and well-defined, while CI is more concerned with outcomes and its mechanisms are extremely hard to define. I thought contrasts like this were fun and sometimes insightful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about CI has a side-effect – it makes me feel like preferring theory to applied, at least in the field of econometrics. When I cannot give my full credence to the validity of the tool, I find it very hard to implement it with no burden on conscience, or else I myself would not even believe in the results. But somehow I’m also scared and unsure of whether I am capable of handling econometric theory. All I know is that now I’m very curious and willing to dive deeper into the topic of CI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels like there’s nothing else to do now but to keep calm and carry on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="CI" /><category term="CI" /><summary type="html">The Story Begins</summary></entry></feed>